<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The present state of the controversie between the Church of England and the Church of Rome, or, An account of the books written on both sides in a letter to a friend.</title>
            <author>Clagett, William, 1646-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69763</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4390</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2767</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11782059</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11782059</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49131</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69763)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49131)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 709:19 or 811:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The present state of the controversie between the Church of England and the Church of Rome, or, An account of the books written on both sides in a letter to a friend.</title>
                  <author>Clagett, William, 1646-1688.</author>
                  <author>Tenison, Thomas, 1636-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Basset, James Adamson, and Tho. Newborough,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in Huntington Library and Duke University Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to William Clagett. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Begun by Tenison and finished by Clagett. cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Ascribed also to Thomas Tenison and William Wake. cf. McAlpin.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49131:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49131:1"/>
            <p>THE
<hi>Preſent State</hi>
OF THE
CONTROVERSIE
BETWEEN THE
Church of <hi>ENGLAND</hi>
AND THE
Church of <hi>ROME;</hi>
OR,
An Account of the Books written
on both ſides. In a LETTER to a Friend.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Guil. Needham,</signed>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>May 7. 1686.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi>:
Printed for <hi>Tho. Baſſet, James Adamſon,</hi> and
<hi>Tho. Newborough,</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:49131:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49131:2"/>
            <head>THE
Preſent State
OF THE
CONTROVERSIE
BETWEEN THE
Church of ENGLAND
AND THE
Church of ROME, &amp;c.
In a LETTER to a Friend.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN purſuance of my promiſe made to you, to
ſend you ſuch an account as you deſire, of what
has been lately publiſhed here, with reference
to the Points in Controverſie between us and
the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> I now give you the
trouble of this Addreſs.</p>
            <p>It was you know the deſign of the Clergy of this
City ſome years ſince, to reduce the matters in debate
with the Diſſenting Party, to a certain number of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49131:3"/>
Caſes, and in the plaineſt and moſt inoffenſive manner
that they could, to ſhew them how little cauſe they
had to ſeparate from our Communion upon any of
thoſe pretences, which were ſaid to be the cauſe of
Separation. I need not tell you what their <hi>Performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi>
were, for you have read their Tracts, and are
therefore able to judg, from your own knowledg,
concerning them. As to the <hi>Succeſs</hi> which they have
had, we that live here, have not only obſerved that
our Churches have been more charged ſince, but do
alſo know, that ſeveral for whoſe ſake thoſe Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
were principally intended, have declared them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
abundantly ſatisfied, both with the ſtrength and
temper that appear'd in them.</p>
            <p>When this firſt undertaking was finiſhed, their next
reſolution was to run through the principal Points of
difference between the Papiſts and us after the ſame
manner, that thoſe who had not the lieſure or oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity
to conſult longer Books, might here in ſhort
be led to a true knowledg of the Controverſie, and
ſtand the firmer in the truth, by being better acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
with the grounds of it. It was alſo hoped, that
many who had hitherto been detained in their Errors
for want not ſo much of a Will to embrace the Truth,
as of Light to diſcern it by, might poſſibly take this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity
of ſeeing with their own eyes, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
that way of Error in which their ignorance or
their prejudices had ſo long detained them.</p>
            <p>But before they had finiſhed this their ſecond un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking,
the ſudden and unexpected Death of our
late Royal Sovereign broke their meaſures, and from
thenceforth they thought fit to be of the Defenſive
ſide, and for ſome time publiſhed no more Diſcourſes
of this kind, but waited to ſee whether the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49131:3"/>
of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion would make any At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taques
upon us, or be contented that the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie
ſhoud reſt as it was.</p>
            <p>But becauſe you deſire an Account of all that has
been done of this nature, I will let you know how
far they advanced in their deſign, and give you a
Catalogue of their Tracts, tho not juſt in the order
as they came out, yet in that order which ſeems to
have been deſign'd, and is moſt natural for you to
peruſe them. And in the firſt place, as a prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory
to all the reſt, there is a little Tract intituled,</p>
            <q>I. A Perſwaſive to an ingenuous Trial of Opinions
in Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>and which they who know the unreaſonable preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices
of thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion, as to any
free enquiry, cannot doubt to have been exceeding
neceſſary. To which I muſt add,</p>
            <q>II. The difference of the Caſe between the ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
of Proteſtants from the Church of
<hi>Rome,</hi> and the ſeparation of Diſſenters from
the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>For both theſe Tracts, as you may eaſily diſcern, were
deſign'd to remove ſuch Miſtakes and Prejudices as
are common to Papiſts and to Diſſenters, and were
therefore thought to be a proper tranſition from
the firſt undertaking to the ſecond.</p>
            <p>Then follow thoſe Treatiſes that relate to the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions
about the Church, and for which our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries
of late ſeem the moſt concern'd.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:49131:4"/>
III. A Diſcourſe of the Unity of the Catholick
Church maintain'd in the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>IV. A Diſcourſe about the Charge of Novelty upon
the Reformed Church of <hi>England,</hi> made by
the Papiſts, aſking of us the Queſtion, Where
was our Religion before <hi>Luther?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>V. The Proteſtant Reſolution of Faith, being
an Anſwer to three Queſtions,
<list>
                     <item>1. How far we muſt depend on the Authority of
the Church for the true ſenſe of Scripture?</item>
                     <item>2. Whether a Viſible Succeſſion from Chriſt to this
day, makes a Church which has this Viſible Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion,
an infallible Interpreter of Scripture?</item>
                     <item>3. Whether the Church of <hi>England</hi> can make out
ſuch a Viſible Succeſſion?</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>VI, VII. Two Diſcourſes concerning the neceſſity
of Reformation, with reſpect to the Errors and
Corruptions of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Another ſort of general Queſtions neceſſary to
have been premiſed to the particular Diſputes, do
refer to the principle on which we are to proceed in
the management of them.</p>
            <p>And to this purpoſe there were publiſhed the two
following Tracts,</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:49131:4"/>
VIII. A Diſcourſe about Tradition, ſhewing what
is meant by it, and what Tradition is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,
and what Tradition is to be rejected.</p>
               <p>IX. A Diſcourſe concerning a Guide in matters
of Faith, with reſpect eſpecially to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh
pretence of ſuch a one as is infallible.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Thus far they proceeded upon general Points, and
no farther, tho more were deſign'd to be debated,
as one may ſee by the dividing and managing of the
Arguments which they finiſhed, and as I my ſelf have
been told by ſome that were beſt able to inform me.</p>
            <p>But as theſe general Diſcourſes were coming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad
into the World; the particular Diſputes were
prepared, and thoſe that follow were publiſhed.</p>
            <q>
               <p>X. A Diſcourſe concerning the Object of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
Worſhip; or, a Scripture Proof of the
unlawfulneſs of giving any Religious Worſhip
to any other Being beſides the Supreme God.</p>
               <p>XI. A Diſcourſe concerning the Devotions of the
Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> eſpecially as compared with
thoſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in which it
is ſhewn, that whatſoever the Romaniſts pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend,
there is not ſo true Devotion among
them, nor ſuch rational proviſion for it, nor
encouragement to it, as in the Church eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by Law amongſt us.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:49131:5"/>
XII. A Diſcourſe concerning the Invocation of
Saints.</p>
               <p>XIII. Of Prayer in an unknown Tongue.</p>
               <p>XIV. Of Auricular Confeſſion, as it is preſcribed
by the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>XV. A Diſcourſe againſt Tranſubſtantiation.</p>
               <p>XVI. Of the Adoration of the Hoſt.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe are the Tracts that were publiſhed in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance
of that Deſign I mention'd before, ſince which
time, our Divines have kept themſelves, as I told
you, upon the Defenſive Part, their whole Work ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
been little elſe than to anſwer ſuch printed
Books, or Papers ſcatter'd about in writing, as the
Romaniſts have from time to time ſent abroad.</p>
            <p>I need not tell you that at length we were ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
with a Book publiſhed by ſome Romaniſt, which
has made no little noiſe all over the Kingdom, and
has been the occaſion of many more: But that
which ſurpriſed us was this, that there was not the
leaſt notice taken in it, of thoſe Diſcourſes now men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned,
and not long before publiſhed in behalf of
the Church of <hi>England</hi> againſt the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The diſcreet Perſons of that Communion acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
they were above Contempt; and it was the
general perſwaſion of our Communion, that they would
not admit of any juſt and reaſonable Anſwer; and
for this very reaſon, ſome appearance of an Anſwer
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49131:5"/>
was generally expected to ſave, if it might be, the
reputation of the <hi>Roman</hi> Cauſe, or at leaſt of the
Ability of our Adverſaries to maintain it, unleſs they
ſhould think fit to let the Controverſie lye ſtill,
which if they had done, I believe our Divines had
thought themſelves obliged by the example, not to
publiſh new Books upon it, but to content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
with that diligence in their Parochial Stations,
that might be ſufficient to countermine any ſecret
endeavours to draw People from the Communion
of this Church: But it ſeems our Adverſaries thought
fit to begin a Diſpute, and that without taking the
leaſt notice of what had been ſo lately done on our
ſide: Which tho we wondred at, at firſt, yet we
have given over wondering at it now that we are
ſomething uſed to their way of Controverſie. For
ſome of them (as the Repreſenter knows) can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
bluſhing for the matter, drop the Defence of
Arguments, and the maintaining of Diſputes begun by
themſelves; and yet they write on ſtill, as if the Cauſe
went for them, and they had not made one falſe ſtep
in the management of it.</p>
            <p>But I muſt now give you a particular account how
theſe Gentlemen began, and in what manner they
carried on that Aſſault, of which it is poſſible they
may have had ſome cauſe to repent them ſince.</p>
            <p>The firſt that led the way, was one that calls him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<hi>R. L.</hi> with a Book full of Cunning and Diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,
intituled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <q>A Papiſt Miſrepreſented and Repreſented.</q>
            <p>In which he runs through moſt of the Points in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie
between us in a two-fold Character; in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49131:6"/>
one of which he pretends to ſhew that which Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts
are commonly miſunderſtood to be; in the other,
that which, as he ſays, they really are.</p>
            <p>The real deſign of this Method, you muſt know is
this. Popery in its proper colours is ſo unlike Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
Chriſtianity, that it is in vain ever to hope to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote
it, if it appear in its own ſhape. It is neceſſary
therefore, that the Religion, like the Prophet, ſhould
come to us in <hi>Sheeps cloathing,</hi> and the Hereſie to be
made look as Orthodox as is poſſible. Some things
are denied, others mollified, all diſguiſed, and a double
benefit thereby obtaind: Popery is to be received as
a very innocent, harmleſs thing; and the Proteſtants,
eſpecially the Miniſters and firſt Reformers repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to the World, as a ſort of People that have ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
themſelves by Calumnies and Lies, and made
a noiſe about Errors and Corruptions, which are no
where to be found, but in their own Brains or Books,
but which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> deteſts no leſs than We.</p>
            <p>But this Trick was quickly diſcovered, and the
deſign laid open by an excellent hand, in a Treatiſe
which he called</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I.</hi> The Doctrines and Practices of the Church of
<hi>Rome</hi> truly repreſented; in anſwer to a Book
intituled, A Papiſt Miſrepreſented and Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which the Author paſſes through every Point of
his Characters, and truly ſtates the Queſtion between
us, and gives a ſhort, yet ſufficient account of our
Reaſons againſt their Tenets.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:49131:6"/>
I ſhall not need enlarge my ſelf to give you any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
of this Controverſie which has been lately ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
up, to ſatisfie the World, that this Author has
taken as little care to defend his Characters, as he
ſhew'd Sincerity in the firſt drawing of them. The
Books themſelves that have paſſed on both ſides are
theſe.</p>
            <q>Reflections upon the Anſwer to the Papiſt Miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented,
&amp;c.</q>
            <q>
               <hi>II.</hi> A Papiſt not Miſrepreſented by Proteſtants,
being a Reply to the Reflections, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Papiſts proteſting againſt Proteſtant Popery; in
Anſwer to a Diſcourſe intituled, A Papiſt not
Miſrepreſented by Proteſtants.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>III.</hi> An Anſwer to a Diſcourſe intituled, Papiſts
proteſting againſt Proteſtant Popery, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
a particular Examination of Monſieur de
<hi>Meaux</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Expoſition
of the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the
Articles of the Invocation of Saints, and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
of Images.</q>
            <p>An Amicable Accommodation of the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
the Repreſenter and the Anſwerer, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn
to his laſt reply.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:49131:7"/>
               <hi>IV.</hi> An Anſwer to the Amicable Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation
of the Difference between
the Repreſenter and the Anſwerer.</q>
            <p>A Reply to the Anſwer to the amicable
Accommodation.</p>
            <p>To which has lately been returned,</p>
            <q>
               <hi>V.</hi> A View of the whole Controverſie
between the Repreſenter and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer,
with an Anſwer to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenters
laſt Reply.</q>
            <p>This is in ſhort the Sum of what has hitherto paſs'd in
this Diſpute, the Miſrepreſenter not having yet taken
any notice of this new Antagoniſt, who it's thought
by ſome, has ſumm'd up this Controverſie ſo effectually,
as to put an end to it. As for his ſecond Part which he
acted afterward under the Character of the Catholick
Repreſenter, I ſhall have occaſion to give you ſome
farther account of it when I come to thoſe Pieces of
our own Divines that have either been the occaſion of,
or the Anſwers to his Sheets and half Sheets.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49131:7"/>
The next that appeared upon the Stage, was the
famous Biſhop of <hi>Condom,</hi> the great Abettor, if not
Founder of this new Sect of Expoſitors of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
and the occaſion of his appearance this. Our
Miſrepreſenter being anſwer'd the firſt time, as has been
ſaid by the Learned Author of the <hi>Doctrines and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices
of the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>truly repreſented.</hi> The new
Method of Expounding and Repreſenting, <hi>i. e.</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling
the good Old Doctrine of the Church began
to ſink; and the People who were principally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd
to be ſeduced by it, generally diſcovered
the Snare that had been laid for them. It was
now too late to recede into the old Popery again.
The Miſrepreſenter had not only forſaken, but in
good meaſure <hi>Anathematiz'd</hi> that, and profeſs'd that
they abhorr'd it no leſs than we; and therefore to
own it now, was in effect to confeſs that we had
reaſon to reform thoſe Errors which themſelves were
once aſhamed to abet: So that what remained, was
to put a good face upon the matter, and ſee if the
Original Pattern, the pompous Expoſition of this
Biſhop, with the long Relation of an Advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
and the glorious Trains of Briefs and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probations
before and behind, might not poſſibly
ſupport the undertaking, and keep up the credit
of their new Popery, which muſt otherwiſe neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily
fall.</p>
            <p>Such was the occaſion, or rather the neceſſity of
publiſhing this Biſhpps Book, which you have ſeen
under the Title of,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:49131:8"/>
The Expoſition of the Doctrine of
the Catholick Church in matters
of Controverſie.</p>
            <p>To which there have been two Anſwers made, of
one of which there has been no notice taken by
the other Party: 'Tis called</p>
            <q>
               <hi>I.</hi> An Anſwer to the Biſhop of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi>'s
Expoſition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
on his Paſtoral Letter.</q>
            <p>The only Excuſe I can think of for the other Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
not replying to this Anſwer, was becauſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
came out before it, which is yet but a lame
pretence, ſince the Book is not only a direct and full
Anſwer to all that was offered by the Biſhop of
<hi>Condom,</hi> either in the way of Expoſition or Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
but has alſo a conſiderable variety of uſeful
Reflections, which perhaps made it more adviſable
to let it alone, than to go about to conſult it.
The other is,</p>
            <q>
               <hi>II.</hi> An Expoſition of the Doctrine of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49131:8"/>
the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the
ſeveral Articles propoſed by the
Biſhop of <hi>Condom,</hi> in his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
of the Doctrine of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick
Faith</q>
            <p>This Anſwer was ſo exquiſite in all its parts, that
it could not fail of gaining a general eſteem; but
the ſuddenneſs in which it was diſpatch'd, rais'd the
admiration of all. And that which made it yet more
taken notice of, was the preface prefix'd to it, in
which the worthy Author (who had the advantage
of informing himſelf of theſe matters, by living ſome
time in <hi>France</hi>) gives a large account of this Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
Expoſition, and of a ſuppreſs'd Edition, which
it ſeems had carried the Trick a little too far, and
therefore was not permitted to ſee the Light, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
with ſome other matters of Fact that very much
laid open the Deſign.</p>
            <p>But to thoſe particulars wherewith you are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
well acquainted, I beg leave to add another
piece of Hiſtory which I have learn'd concerning
this matter.</p>
            <p>You muſt underſtand then the project of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting
the <hi>French</hi>-Proteſtants, which has been more
or leſs carried on ever ſince <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth's time,
was more eſpecially agitated at the concluſion of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49131:9"/>
               <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty almoſt 30 years ſince: The <hi>Spaniards</hi>
being apprehenſive of the <hi>French</hi> Power, and willing
to divert it by an undertaking, which they thought
might find them work at home, and not leave them
at leiſure to diſturb their Neighbours. It was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved
there, at the ſame time that the Civil Power
began to oppreſs them, the Church ſhould offer ſome
Terms of a Reunion to them, and all poſſible en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours
be uſed to encline them to accept it: To
this end Money was ſecretly given to ſeveral of the
Miniſters, to favour this Project; but the Deſign be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
diſcover'd by a Miniſter of <hi>Bas-Languedoc,</hi> the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod
of <hi>Niſmes, Ann.</hi> 1662. and that of <hi>Cevennes</hi> being
aſſembled not long after, appeard ſo vigorouſly againſt
it, that they were forc'd to lay aſide the Deſign for
ſome time. About Ten years after it broke out
again; but the Miniſters of <hi>Languedoc</hi> and the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod
of the Iſle of <hi>France</hi> oppoſing it, as thoſe of
<hi>Niſmes</hi> and <hi>Cevennes</hi> had done before, it came to
nothing.</p>
            <p>Now this ſecond attempt was dated preciſely
at the ſame time that the Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
began to ſee the Light: And that which
convinces me that it was purpoſely contriv'd for
the advancing this Deſign is this, that the Marſhal
de <hi>Turene,</hi> who was this Biſhops Convert, and
the principal Defender of this Expoſition, was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
at the ſame time the great Undertaker for this
Project. 'Tis well known how to this end he ſent
a Perſon through the ſeveral Provinces of <hi>France,</hi>
with private Inſtructions to thoſe Miniſters, which
he thought he could moſt influence to cloſe with it:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49131:9"/>
And in effect he did obtain ſeveral of their Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions,
whom when the Proteſtant Synods would
afterwards have cenſur'd for their ſo doing, the
Kings Commiſſioners took their parts, and would
not ſuffer them to do it.</p>
            <p>And here I ought not to forget one particular
which may be worth your knowledg, and that is
this. Among others to whom the <hi>Marſhal</hi> ſent,
one was the famous Monſieur le <hi>Blanc,</hi> he was at
that time Priſoner at <hi>Sedan,</hi> and the moderation
that he ſhewed in ſtating the Controverſies of
<hi>Grace, Free-Will, Predeſtination,</hi> &amp;c. gave them
great hopes that he might eaſily be drawn in to
the favouring their Project of an Accomodation
with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by meeting one another
half way. The Agent brought him a Letter from
Monſieur de <hi>Turene</hi> to this purpoſe, but was mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
ſurprized, when inſtead of what he expected,
hee found him ſtiff and inflexible, and abſolutely
reſolved not to relax any thing. Indeed the very
attempt that was made upon him, ſo diſturbed him,
that he could not be ſatisfied with his private re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentmeut
of it, but in the year 1673. publiſhed a
Diſputation to them, that the re-union which they
had attempted with the <hi>Lutherans</hi> made nothing to
one with the Papiſts, which he there ſhews to be
impoſſible.</p>
            <p>This with what you have read in the Preface
to the Tract, which has occaſiond this Digreſſion,
may ſeem to ſatisfie you, what the Quality of the
Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Expoſition is, and what intreague
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49131:10"/>
it was deſigned to ſerve. You have the <hi>Politiques
of the Clergy of</hi> France, in which Book you may
ſee the very Propoſitions that were made for this
Accommodation, and which are a pure Original of
New Popery, and ſo conformable to the French
Expoſitor, and our Engliſh Miſrepreſenter, that you
cannot doubt but that they all deſigned to carry on
the ſame Deſign.</p>
            <p>For the little value that is to be ſet upon the
Approbations prefix'd to it: The Author of the
Expoſition of the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi>
has I think ſaid enough to ſatifie you: To
which you may add, that in the late Diviſions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
the <hi>Janſeniſts</hi> and their Oppoſers in <hi>France,</hi>
the Books on both ſides have been very ſolemnly
approved, and the <hi>Janſeniſts</hi> above any. And in
the preſent Caſe, either the Approbations of the
Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi>'s Expoſition ſignifie nothing, or
thoſe heretofore prefix'd to Cardinal <hi>Bellarmines</hi>
Works, and their other learned Controvertiſts are
become ſuper-annuated; for all theſe cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
ſtand together.</p>
            <p>But I run too far from my buſineſs, and muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn
to our Expoſitor, who was not long without
an Anſwer, entituled</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49131:10"/>
               <hi>IV.</hi> A Vindication of the Biſhop of
<hi>Condom</hi>'s Expoſition, with a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
from the ſaid Biſhop.</q>
            <p>I will not tire you with giving my own ſenſe of the
Performances of any whoſe Titles I ſend you, and
whoſe Books I leave you to judg of when you read
them. I will only obſerve to you, that we are very
much beholding to the Biſhop, with confeſſing the
particulars wich his Adverſary had charged him
with, and which there are many that before did
hardly believe. And for his Excuſes which he
makes, the truth is, they are ſo little to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
that he has gain'd but little credit even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
his Friends by them. And if this be as they
ſay, the firſt notice he ever took of any Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
that appeared againſt him, he would do very
well to have a care of ſetting out Vindications of
his Works, at which he appears to be ſo horribly
unlucky.</p>
            <p>But for all this you may recur to the Reply
that has been made by the ſame Author who wrote
the Expoſition of our Doctrine in his ſecond under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking,
alled</p>
            <q>
               <hi>V.</hi> A Defence of the Expoſition of
the Doctrine of the Church of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49131:11"/>
               <hi>England,</hi> againſt the Exceptions
of the Biſhop of <hi>Condom</hi> and
his Vindicator.</q>
            <p>In which beſides an Anſwer to the Biſhops Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
and a particular review of all the ſeveral Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles
in debate, you will find in the <hi>Appendix</hi> ſome
Pieces that will gratifie your Curioſity, relating to
the Point of the Invocation of Saints. And in the
cloſe of all, the Epiſtle of S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> to <hi>Caeſarius,</hi>
which had been indeed very baſely ſuppreſs'd by
by them, but is now happily recovered, to the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
reproach of thoſe who have ſo often and
confidently urged the Authority of that Father for
to ſupport their new Hereſie of Tranſubſtantiation,
and which he here in as plain words ſpeaks againſt,
as if <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> had not only firſt produced, but
as ſome of them have ſaid, had written the Epiſtle
for him.</p>
            <p>And thus far this Controverſie has proceeded,
which at preſent ſtops here, though the Reverend
Father who writ the Vindication, had prepar'd us
to expect that it ſhould not long do ſo, But we
now begin to think, that both the Vindicator and
the Repreſenter, are ſenſible that their deſign will
not bear being driven on any further.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49131:11"/>
But tho we have done with the buſineſs of the Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,
yet we muſt not ſo ſoon part with the Biſhop.
For ſince the Publication of that, theſe new Popery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
have favour'd the World with two other of his
Pieces, the
<list>
                  <item>1. A Paſtoral Letter to the New-Converts of
his Dioceſs. <hi>The</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. A Treatiſe of Communion under one kind.</item>
               </list>
            </q>
            <p>The latter of theſe which had drawn in <hi>French</hi> an
admirable Anſwer heretofore, from that exact Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,
Monſieur <hi>Larroque;</hi> which 'tis ſaid, the Biſhop him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
thought too ſtrong to be anſwer'd with any advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage;
has alſo not long ſince produced us a Treatiſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
worthy your peruſing in our own Language, intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</p>
            <q>A Diſcourſe of the Communion in one Kind,
in Anſwer to a Treatiſe of the Biſhop of
Meaux, of Communion, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>And in the two Diſcourſes, I mean the Biſhops and
the Anſwer, you may expect to find whatever Artifice
and Inſincerity can do on one ſide, or Truth and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
reply on the other.</p>
            <p>For what concerns his Paſtoral Letter, I have ſeen ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
Anſwers to it in <hi>French,</hi> and one particularly very
accurately done, called <hi>Reponſe à Monſr. L'Eveque de</hi>
Meaux <hi>ſur ſa lettre Paſtorale;</hi> which if you think fit, I
will ſend you: I do not know that any one has particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly
undertaken it here, any farther than what was done
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49131:12"/>
by the Author of the ſecond Anſwer to his Expoſition,
who made ſome Reflections upon the Paſtoral Letter
too.</p>
            <p>In this Letter, there is one notable paſſage; and the
account of which, becauſe you may not perhaps meet
with elſewhere, I will run the hazard of another Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion
to offer it you here. In the <hi>3d</hi> page, there is
ſet in Capital Letters, this notable Declaration, <hi>Not one
of you hath ſuffer'd Violence, either in his Perſon or Goods.</hi>
And page 4. <hi>So far,</hi> ſays he, <hi>have you been from ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Torments, that you have not ſo much as heard them
mentioned; I hear other Biſhops affirm the ſame: You are
returned peaceably to us, you know it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I doubt not but this Paſſage a little ſurpriſed you, as
it did all the World that ever read it; being ſo contrary
to all the Accounts that have come from thence. Indeed
His M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>j<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſties Brief alone may ſerve for a Confutation
to ſo ſhameful an Aſſertion, and ſhew us how little we
can rely upon thoſe Gentlemen, when they talk to us
of things that were done 12. or 14. years ago, that make
no ſcruple of dealing thus with us in a matter of Fact,
in the ſight of the World, before whoſe Eyes theſe
things are acted: Nay, to tell the very Proteſtants
themſelves, that they had ſuffer'd no Violence, that they
knew it, when the contrary was as evident to them,
as that their Hoſt is not the Body of a Man; and no
doubt the Biſhop might as eaſily be able to prove the one,
as with all his fine Words perſwade the other.</p>
            <p>But I will open to you the Mytery of this. You muſt
know then, That, as far as I can learn, the Dragoons
were not lodged in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Meaux;</hi> but yet
they came up to the very Gates of the City. Being
thus in ſight of their Danger, and expecting every mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute
when it would fall upon them, the Biſhop thought
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49131:12"/>
that certainly now, if ever, they would be diſpoſed to
compliance.</p>
            <p>With this advantage he invites them to a Conference,
appears more moderate than even his own Expoſition;
and deſires very little more of them than what any one
might venture to ſubſcribe. Such advances backt with
ſo good an Authority as the Dragoons at the Gates, could
not but prevail upon them; they ſubſcribed as he deſired,
and ſo the Dragoons were diſmiſſed without doing
them any farther miſchief.</p>
            <p>In this ſtate, they continued for about three months,
when the Biſhop began to Viſit his Dioceſs, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially,
thoſe parts in which there were the moſt Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.
His carriage upon this review was very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
from what it had been before. He was now no
longer the free, relaxing, good natur'd Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi>
that held the Conference with them, but rigid as any
little Emiſſary. He threatned thoſe, who refuſed to
go to Maſs, and aſſiſt at the other Offices of the Church;
and tho ſeveral told him that this was not what he had
promiſed them, yet he took but little notice of it.
Monſ. <hi>de Soguier,</hi> Lord of <hi>Charmoi,</hi> and Couſin to
the late Chancellor <hi>Soguier,</hi> and ſeveral others more
obſtinate than the reſt, both had the Dragoons quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd
upon them in his Dioceſs, and are at this day Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners
upon this Account. This I have read in ſome
late <hi>French</hi> Pieces, which have taken notice of it; but
the main of what I ſend you, is an extract of a Letter,
which was written to a Friend of mine out of <hi>France;</hi>
and who being himſelf not long ſince there, confirm'd
to me ſeveral of thoſe Particulars, as to this Biſhops
Dioceſs.</p>
            <p>I preſume you have heard how this Biſhop, who in
his Paſtoral Letter dated <hi>March</hi> 24. denies, as you ſee,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49131:13"/>
that there has been any thing of violence uſed to the
Proteſtants in <hi>France,</hi> did in another Letter to a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
of Quality that had eſcaped thence, and whom he
deſired to draw back if poſſible to his Country, and
his Church, both own and juſtifie the Perſecution.
This Letter was dated but <hi>Apr.</hi> 4. after the other. This
Honourable perſon had ſuch indignation againſt him
for his double dealing, that he has permitted the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
Letter to him, to be printed; and which agrees as
well with his Paſtoral Letter, as his Expoſition does
with Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi>'s Controverſies; the Old Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery
from whence we reformed, with the New by which
they would now ſeduce us.</p>
            <p>A third ſubject there has been for a more important
Controverſie than either of the foregoing, occaſioned
by the Papers left by His Majeſty concerning the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
of the Catholick Church; and the Method of
which lies thus:</p>
            <p>The two Papers written by the late King
<hi>Charles</hi> the Second.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>The Anſwer intituled,</hi> An Anſwer to ſome
Papers lately printed concerning the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
of the Catholick Church in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
of Faith, and the Reformation of
the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To theſe there came out almoſt at the ſame time two
Replies.</p>
            <q>A Defence of the Papers written by the late
King of Bleſſed Memory.</q>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:49131:13"/>
In which there is little remarkable beſides the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handſome
levity of the ſtile, and the ungrateful drolls
in a matter of ſo much ſeriouſneſs.</p>
            <q>A Reply to the Anſwer made upon the Three
Royal Papers.</q>
            <p>This is much more to be commended both for its
ſtrength and decency; and they would perhaps much
more have ſerved the intereſt of their Cauſe, and ſhewn
their reſpect to His late Majeſty, had they ſuffer'd no
other to appear.</p>
            <p>But to both of them the ſame worthy Author who
wrote the former Reply, has very lately publiſht a moſt
Learned and Excellent Anſwer, and which I would very
much recommend to your careful conſideration, Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled,</p>
            <q>2 A Vindication of the Anſwer to ſome late
Papers concerning the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Authority
of the Catholick Church, and the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>A Diſcourſe ſo Learnedly and clearly written, that
we ought to thank our Adverſaries for their importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
that has produced us ſo excellent a Treatiſe in a
Point of ſuch importance.</p>
            <p>I think I have now ſet down all the Diſputes that
have proceeded to any length this laſt year: For the
reſt, they are either ſuch as you may call Occaſional
Treatiſes only, or ſuch as are not advanced into any
ſet and regular debates.</p>
            <p>I. Of the former kind I underſtand theſe following:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49131:14"/>
Firſt, concerning St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Supremacy, a Diſcourſe
Intituled,</p>
            <q>A Sermon preacht upon Saint <hi>Peter</hi>'s Day,
printed at the deſire of ſome that heard it,
with ſome Enlargements.</q>
            <p>The Occaſion of which was this: Dr. <hi>Godden</hi> had
the laſt year publiſhed a Sermon on this Subject which
he preacht in the Q. Dowagers Chappel; whereupon
the Reverend Author of this Diſcourſe having likewiſe
preacht on the ſame day, and upon the ſame Text, was
prevailed with to print his too.</p>
            <p>Another Subject that has Occaſionally produced us
two or three very good Treatiſes, is, <q>
                  <hi>The Worſhip of
Saints:</hi>
               </q> Our late Miſrepreſenter and the Biſhop of
<hi>Meaux</hi>'s Expoſition having been pleaſed very much to
palliate the Doctrine and Practice of the Church of
<hi>Rome</hi> as to this matter; and pretending that what they
now do is no more than what was done even in the
Fourth Age of the Church; it was neceſſary ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
diſcovery ſhould be made of this Artifice, and
it has accordingly been done very effectually in the
following Tracts.</p>
            <q>2 <hi>Speculum B. Virginis;</hi> A Diſcourſe of the
due Praiſe and Honour of the Virg. <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>In which is clearly ſet forth what we allow, and what
the bold extravagancy of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> has car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri'd
them to do in the Worſhip of the Bleſſed Virgin.</p>
            <q>3 A Diſcourſe of the Worſhip of the Bleſſed
Virgin and the Saints, with an account of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49131:14"/>
the beginning and riſe of it among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
in Anſwer to <hi>Monſieur de Meaux</hi>'s
Appeal to the Fourth Age in his Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
and Paſtoral Letter.</q>
            <q>4 Wholſome Advices from the Bleſſed Virgin
to Her indiſcreet Worſhippers.</q>
            <p>This laſt is but a Tranſlation: It was written origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally
by a Papiſt, one Mr. <hi>Widenfelt,</hi> a Perſon of good
Eſteem and Reputation in his Country; who being
Scandalized at the extravagant Practices of his Church
in this matter, wrote this little Treatiſe to awaken their
Conſideration, and if poſſible, reduce the People from
their uſual extravagance, to the Temper and Moderation
of the preſent Advocates for their Cauſe, as to this
matter. But alas! He found them too fond of their Old
Popery, to leave it ſo eaſily: Inſtead of doing any good
upon them, his Book was cenſured in a very extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
manner, and the Honour of the Bleſſed Virgin
vindicated againſt theſe new Hereticks, by her faithful
Champion Father <hi>Craſſet</hi> the Jeſuit: A ſhort Specimen
of whoſe Book you may ſee at the end of the <hi>Defence
of the Expoſition of the Doctrine of the Church of England;</hi>
or if you had rather have it from their own Pens, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
none can better expoſe their Extravagancies of
this kind, than they have done themſelves, you may
then conſult a late Popiſh Book called,</p>
            <q>Contemplations on the life and glory of Holy
<hi>Mary</hi> the Mother of Jeſus; With a daily
Office agreeing to each Myſtery thereof. By
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49131:15"/>
               <hi>J. C. D. D. To which he has ſince added,</hi>
An Apology for his Contemplations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>But of all this, you will find a particular account in
an excellent Preface prefixt to theſe Advices by the
Tranſlator of it; who profeſſes himſelf to be a Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
of our Church, and has the character of a very
worthy, as he has ſufficiently ſhewn himſelf to be a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
ingenious Gentleman.</p>
            <p>It may be proper here to remark, that this Preface
has been attacked by the Catholick Repreſenter; or the
Miſrepreſenter transformed: in his <hi>4th</hi> Chapter of his
Second part; and to which he has returned a ſmart Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,
called,</p>
            <q>5. A Letter to the Miſrepreſenter of Papiſts.</q>
            <p>Another occaſional Treatiſe came forth not long
ſince, intituled,</p>
            <q>6. A Diſcourſe concerning a Judg of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies
in matters of Religion; With an
Addreſs to wavering Proteſtants, ſhewing
what little Reaſon they have to think of
any change of their Religion.</q>
            <p>It was written in Anſwer to ſome Papers that had
been ſent to the Learned Author, by a Perſon of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,
aſſerting the neceſſity of ſuch a Judg. If I ſhould
tell you from whoſe Pen this Treatiſe came, you would
need no other inducement carefully to read it. And
to encourage you to it, I will only ſay thus much,
that it has been generally received with great Applauſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49131:15"/>
here, and do's certainly as well deſerve it, as any thing
that has hitherto been publiſh'd among us.</p>
            <p>Here has been publiſhed likewiſe a ſhort Tract con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
the nature of the Catholick Church, and the
Authority of it.</p>
            <p>It is not level'd againſt any particular Author; but
deſign'd to anſwer the little captious Arguments now
much in vogue; and therefore, neceſſary to have been
thus prevented: The chief points handled in it, are theſe
three. 1. What is the Nature of the Catholick Church.
2. That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is not the Catholick
Church. 3. That the Holy Scriptures, and not the
Church, are the Rule of Faith. The Title of this
Treatiſe, is this,</p>
            <q>7. A plain and Familiar Diſcourſe by way of
Dialogue, betwixt a Miniſter and his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioner
concerning the Catholick Church.</q>
            <p>To theſe I may add a Treatiſe, concerning the defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> from what it once was. It
is an Anſwer to a Popiſh Paper, which the Author has
Printed at the beginning of his Book, given about it ſeems
by thoſe of that party, and ſent by way of Letter to a
Gentleman: It is called,</p>
            <q>8. An Anſwer to a late Paper given about
by ſome of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Another Subject that has occaſionally been handled, is,
concerning Schiſm and Hereſy: It is an Anſwer to ſome
things in a Popiſh Pamphlet, called, <hi>Why, are you a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick?</hi>
The Author treats of the Nature of theſe two,
and enquires to which Church it is that they really do
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49131:16"/>
belong: In ſhort, Whether the Papiſts or we, are Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks
and Hereticks? The Title is this,</p>
            <q>9. A Vindication of the Church of <hi>England</hi>
from the foul Aſperſions of Schiſm and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy,
unjuſtly caſt upon Her by the Church
of <hi>Rome. In two Parts.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>The laſt Subject that has occaſionally, but yet more
copiouſly been handled, and which upon that Account,
I reſerved to this place, is concerning the Worſhip of
Images, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It began by this means. A Reverend Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
of our Church, took occaſion from the late Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
of our Miſrepreſenting the Opinions of the Papiſts,
to ſet forth an excellent Catechiſm, called</p>
            <q>10. A Catechiſm truly repreſenting the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines
and Practices of the Church of
<hi>Rome,</hi> with an Anſwer unto them.</q>
            <p>It is not to be wonder'd that ſuch a Book as this
ſhould be thought proper to be ſet forth; When the
whole buſineſs of thoſe of the other Communion, was
to palliate by any means the true Doctrines and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices
of their Church; it certainly became us to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
them to the World, as indeed they are. This has
here been done from their own Authors, and with
great Sincerity. But notwithſtanding this, the Miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter
that then was, in one of his Anſwers to the
firſt great Controverſy I have mentioned, took him to
task for it: In the cloſe of a new Edition of this Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm,
an anſwer was made to his Exceptions. Not
long after this, the Miſrepreſenter began a new under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49131:16"/>
to oblige the World with a Sheet a week, firſt;
called <hi>the Second Part of the Papiſt Repreſented and
Miſrepreſented;</hi> and after, of half a Sheet, which he has
continued to the number of ſixteen Chapters, under
the new Character of the Catholick Repreſenter. In
his <hi>1ſt, 2d, 5th</hi> and <hi>6th</hi> Sheets or Chapters, he falls
upon the Author of this Catechiſm, with reference
to the Point of the Worſhip of Images, and of the Croſs;
which has produced us three ſhort, but yet excellent
Anſwers, called
<q>11.
<list>
                     <item>1. The Papiſts Repreſented and not Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſented,
in Anſwer to the firſt
Sheet of the Second part.</item>
                     <item>2. The like to the Second. <hi>And</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. To the Fifth and Sixth.</item>
                  </list>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The buſineſs of all which is the ſame, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſhew
what the true Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is in the
Points hefore mention'd, <hi>Of the Worſhip of Images, and
of the Croſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the other ſort of Tracts that have been written,</p>
            <q>II. More immediatly in Anſwer to ſome of their ſet
Diſcourſes.</q>
            <p>They have alſo been on different Subjects: Such as
theſe.</p>
            <q>(1.) Concerning Tranſubſtantiation.</q>
            <p>Upon which their late Attempts, either to ſet up that,
or to ruin the other Myſteries of the Goſpel, but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,
that of the Trinity, have occaſioned ſeveral ſhort,
but accurate Diſcourſes: I ſhall ſend you the Titles of
them.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:49131:17"/>
1. The Anſwer to the Popiſh Dialogue between a new
Catholick Convert and a Proteſtant, to prove the
Myſtery of the Trinity to be as abſurd a D<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctrine as
Tranſubſtantiation: By way of ſhort Notes upon the
ſaid Dialogue.</p>
               <p>2. The Doctrine of the Trinity and Tranſubſtantiation
compared, as to Scripture, Reaſon, and Tradition:
<hi>In Anſwer to the ſame, and in two Parts.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>To which I will add for the Affinity of the Subject,
two other Treatiſes, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>3. A Paraphraſe with Notes, and a Preface upon the
6th Chapter of St. <hi>John,</hi> ſhewing that there is
neither good Reaſon, nor ſufficient Authority to
ſuppoſe that the Euchariſt is diſcourſed of in that
Chapter, much leſs to infer the Doctrine of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation
from it.</p>
               <p>4. An Hiſtorical Treatiſe of Tranſubſtantiation, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
by an Author of the Communion of the Church of
<hi>Rome:</hi> Wherein is made appear, that according to
the Principles of that Church, this Doctrine cannot
be an Article of Faith.</p>
            </q>
            <p>To theſe Diſcourſes upon this ſubject, we cannot
more fitly add any thing, than what has lately been
done on another relating to the Holy Euchariſt, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>(2.) Concerning the Real Preſence, and Adoration of
the Hoſt.</q>
            <p>You ought to know very well what gave occaſion to
this Controverſie; <hi>viz.</hi> the two Diſcourſes ſet out by
Mr. <hi>W</hi>—at <hi>Oxford</hi> on this Subject. As for the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
to them, it was ſent you into the Country, and
bears this Title:</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:49131:17"/>
5. A Diſcourſe of the Holy Euchariſt in the two great
Points of the Real Preſence, and of the Adoration of
the Hoſt; in Anſwer to the two Diſcourſes ſet forth at
<hi>Oxford</hi> on the ſame Subject.</q>
            <p>It was I believe expected that this Controverſie would
have either expoſed our Church, had we own'd the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant
notion of the Real Preſence Mr. <hi>W</hi>—would
put upon us, and which is indeed Couſin Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
to Tranſubſtantiation; or have raiſed, it may be, a
Civil War amongſt us, if we did not. But I believe both
their expectations will fail them; for certainly whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
ſome particular perſons may have believed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
yet the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is
plainly as the Anſwerer has repreſented it; and as we
expect it will be farther proved in the other Reply
which we are told is preparing at <hi>Oxford</hi> by an Eminent
Perſon there to the ſame Book.</p>
            <p>There is prefixt to this extant, a very large Preface,
which has properly enough retorted Mr. <hi>W</hi>'s—Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
and ſhewn the World that if other Divines (as
he pretends) have believed a Subſtantial Preſence of
Chriſt's Natural Body in the Holy Euchariſt, 'tis more
than many of the moſt Eminent of theirs have done,
who are here plainly diſcover'd not to have believed
Tranſubſtantiation.</p>
            <p>A third Subject that has given occaſion to another
Anſwer, is what they have called <hi>a Proteſtants plea for
a Socinian.</hi> The deſign was to prove, that in interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
Scripture by Reaſon, and not ſubmitting to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible
Interpretation of what they call the Church,
we make an Apology for the <hi>Socinians,</hi> and all other
Hereticks whatſoever. The falſeneſs of this Pretence has
been at large ſhewn in the Anſwer which an Eminent
perſon of our Church has lately put out to it, called,</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:49131:18"/>
6. The Difference between the Proteſtant and <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi>
Methods, in Anſwer to a Book, Entituled, A
Proteſtants Plea for a <hi>Socinian.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>In which beſides a full account of this matter, you
will find many other Curioſities relating to the Method
and Principles of the <hi>Socinians,</hi> which you have never
it may be elſwhere met with.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To theſe I may add the Anſwers that have been ſet
forth by way of Notes on ſome Papers called,</hi> Lucilla
and Elizabeth, or the Donatiſt and Proteſtant Schiſms
parallel'd. <hi>And,</hi> A Requeſt to Proteſtants to produce plain
Scripture directly authorizing certain Tenets, which he
there ſubjoins. <hi>The Anſwers are called,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>7. A Proteſtant of the Church of <hi>England</hi> no <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſt.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>8. An Anſwer to the Request to Proteſtants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Which laſt Anſwer has had a Reply called, <hi>Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
destitute of Scripture-proof,</hi> againſt which there is, I
am told, a Defence of the Anſwer now in the Preſs.</p>
            <p>There are ſome other little things which I ought
not to forget, becauſe they have done a great deal of
good.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>As,</hi> The plain mans Reply to the Catholick Miſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries.</q>
            <q>
               <hi>And</hi> An Anſwer to the Eighth Chapter of the
Repreſenters ſecond Part in the firſt Dialogue between
him and his Lay-friend.</q>
            <p>Publiſhed by the Lay-man of whom I have ſpoken
above. As for the Conference at the D. of <hi>P.</hi> which you
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49131:18"/>
have heard of, one Mr<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> G. who maintained the <hi>Roman</hi>
ſide, tried to reſolve the Infallibility of the Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<hi>Oral Tradition,</hi> and afterwards boaſted ſo unmeaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably
of the Advantages he had made of the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,
that he drew upon himſelf a juſt rebuke in a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
Paper called,</p>
            <q>A Letter to Mr. <hi>G.</hi> concerning the Conference at the
<hi>D.</hi> of <hi>P.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Which having produced two Letters from the other
ſide, there preſently came forth,</p>
            <q>A ſecond Letter to Mr. <hi>G.</hi> in Anſwer to Two Letters
lately publiſhed concerning the Conference at the <hi>D.</hi> of <hi>P.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>There is alſo lately publiſhed a Diſcourſe by an Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious
and worthy Gentleman, concerning the Authority
of Councils, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to which is added a ſhort but an effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual
Anſwer to the Eighth <hi>Theſes,</hi> by which Mr. <hi>W.—</hi>
in his Part V. of Church-Government pretends to try
the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Reformation. The Title is,</p>
            <q>Of the Authority of Councils, and the Rule of Faith.
By a Perſon of Quality. With an Anſwer to the Eight
Theſes laid down for the Trial of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
in the Book that came last Week from <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>After which there came forth a Diſcourſe which is
here exceedingly well received, and the Deſign whereof
is ſufficiently explained by the Title, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>An Apologetical Vindication of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
in Anſwer to thoſe who reproach her with the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi>
Hereſies and Schiſms, or ſuſpect her not to be a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick
Church upon their account.</q>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:49131:19"/>
I ought not to conceal the Anſwer to that Libel up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the Reformation which you have ſeen, called <hi>Pax
Vobis;</hi> though it is not a juſt Anſwer to the Book, but
a Preface rather to more that is to follow. The Title is</p>
            <q>Some Dialogues between Mr. <hi>G.</hi> and others, with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexions
upon a Book called <hi>Pax Vobis.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>When the Anſwerer has finiſhed his deſign, you may
have what remains, as I am told under the ſame Title.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude your Trouble at preſent with telling
you of a Sett of Diſcourſes concerning the Notes of the
Church, as they are laid down by <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> Thus far
the Deſign has proceeded already.</p>
            <q>
               <list>
                  <item>1. A Brief Diſcourſe concerning the Notes of the
Church, with ſome Reflexions on Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi>'s
Notes.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Bellarmine</hi>'s firſt Note of the Church, concerning
the Name of <hi>Catholick</hi> examined.</item>
                  <item>3. The 2d Note of the Church examined, <hi>viz.</hi> Antiquity.</item>
                  <item>4. The 3d Note of the Church examined, <hi>viz.</hi> Duration.</item>
               </list>
            </q>
            <p>I perceive we may expect the reſt in Order. I am Sir,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:49131:19"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49131:20"/>
            <p>Imprimatur, Liber cui Titulus, <hi>[An Anſwer to the Repreſenter's Reflections
upon the View of the Controverſie, with a Reply to the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator's
Full Anſwer.]</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Jan. 21. 1687.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>H. Maurice,</hi> R<hi rend="sup">mo.</hi> in Chriſto
P. D. Wilhelmo Archiep.
Cant. a Sacris.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49131:20"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
